Okay, tumor progression.
Once you've understood the idea of carcinogenesis
and you understand that carcinogenesis
is going to knock out key important regulatory elements,
then the next notion is that as a tumor cell grows
and begins to produce additional daughter cells,
it will pick up additional mutations.
And those additional mutations
will allow for tumor progression.
And so eventually what will happen in the case of cancer
is that accumulation of mutations
will result in invasion and spread.
And remember that the hallmark of cancer,
of malignant neoplasia,
is that it locally invades
and the defining feature of malignant neoplasia or cancer
is that it will spread to distant sites,
which is also called metastasis.
Now in order for this spread to occur,
there are a few characteristic changes
that have to arise within the tumor
to promote such spread.
And so what I'd like to do is walk you through those.
The first is downregulation of E-cadherin.
Normally, when you look at epithelial cells,
these are epithelial cells,
you're well aware from histology
that epithelial cells sit on a basement membrane
and that these epithelial cells
are attached to each other by various molecules,
one subgroup of which is called the cadherins.
And within cadherin,
a particular molecule is e-cadherin.
Now, cadherins,
they keep the cells attached to one another.
And if tumor is going to form,
for example, from this cell,
what needs to happen in order for it
to be able to spread locally
and then to metastasize
is this tumor cell needs to be able
to dissociate from its neighbors.
One way by which it dissociates from its neighbors
is via a downregulation of E-cadherin.
And so one characteristic that I've listed here
in your text is downregulation of E-cadherin.
Now, once E-cadherin is downregulated,
then this cell will attach to the laminin,
which is present in association
with the basement membrane.
Go back and recall from normal histology
that the basement membrane
is basically composed of two key molecules.
The first is collagen IV.
Collagen IV makes up the vast majority
of the basement membrane.
And then the basement membrane
also has laminin associated with it.
And so the cells,
once they dissociate from the neighboring cells,
will actually attach to the laminin
within the basement membrane.
Now, once they attach to the laminin
within the basement membrane,
the next step would be
to destroy the basement membrane.
And tumor cells can eventually develop
the ability to produce collagenase,
in particular collagenase
that would destroy collagen type IV.
Binding to the laminin
and destruction of the basement membrane
will then allow this cell
to eventually come out here
into the extracellular matrix.
Now, once the cell
is within the extracellular matrix,
it will attach itself to fibronectin.
It'll attach itself to fibronectin
within the extracellular matrix,
and then it can spread locally.
Eventually, it'll gain access
to either the blood vessel,
or it may gain access to lymphatics.
And when it gains access to lymphatics,
it'll spread to lymph node.
And if it gains access to blood vessel,
it will spread to distant sites.
And so this is sort of a little bit
of a paradigm, step number one,
down-regulation of e-cadherin.
Step number two,
the cells then attach to laminin.
Step number three,
they destroy the basement membrane
using collagenase type IV.
Step number four,
they attach to fibronectin
in the extracellular matrix
and begin to spread locally.
And then step number five
would be to enter into the vascular
or lymphatic space.
And if we go back to the slide,
each of these steps is listed here
in sequence,
and you can review this
within your text as well.
I've already basically explained
this slide to you.
Recall that one of the hallmarks
or the key hallmark
of a malignant tumor,
i.e. cancer,
is that it will spread to distant sites.
And so it's important to know
that carcinomas,
they tend to spread via the lymphatics.
So the place where you expect
to see carcinoma
would be the regional draining lymph nodes.
I'll just give you one example.
Take, for example, breast cancer.
So when a patient develops breast cancer,
one of the common sites
or one of the initial sites of spread
is into the lymphatics
and then through the lymphatics
into the axillary lymph nodes.
And recall that the axillary lymph nodes
are the lymph nodes
that drain the breast.
And so one important principle
to know about cancer
is that carcinoma spread
via lymphatics to regional nodes.
General principle.
Carcinoma spread
via lymphatics
to regional lymph nodes.
To highlight this,
I've placed a picture in your text.
And you can clearly see
what I've,
this picture basically
is that of a lymph node.
So I'm highlighting here
the capsule of the lymph node.
This area here
represents the normal lymph node
with these small dark blue cells.
And then clearly,
we can see
that there is some tumor here
which is replacing the lymph node.
And notice that the tumor
has a bunch of
white spaces within it.
And these are glands.
And this is an adenocarcinoma.
And so I've only placed this here
to remind you
of the general principle
that carcinomas
tend to spread
via the lymphatics
into regional lymph nodes.
Cancer can also spread
hematogenously.
And hematogenous spread
is characteristic of sarcomas.
Recall from the beginning
of this lecture
that sarcomas are
a malignancy
of mesenchymal tissue.
So for example,
an osteosarcoma
is a malignant bone tumor.
A chondrosarcoma
is a malignant cartilage tumor.
A liposarcoma
is a malignant tumor
of adipose tissue.
So mesenchymal
or connective tissues
when they're malignant,
we call them sarcomas.
And sarcomas
tend to spread
through the blood.
They go into the blood vessels
and then they spread
to distant sites.
So that's a general principle.
So principle A
of this discussion,
principle A
is that carcinomas
go into the lymphatics
and spread
to the regional lymph nodes.
And principle B
would be that sarcomas
go into the blood
and a characteristic
site of spread
would be the lungs.
Now,
there are some exceptions
and so the exceptions
become high yield
because they make
for nice test material.
There are a subset
of carcinomas
that like to spread
into the blood.
And so again,
they're breaking the rule.
And so it's important
to be familiar
with these exceptions
because again,
it makes for nice
test material.
So one exception
is renal cell carcinoma.
And renal cell carcinoma,
it's one of the characteristics
of renal cell carcinoma
is that it likes
to invade
into the renal vein.
And when it invades
into the renal vein,
it can present
with distant metastases.
And it's not uncommon
for a patient
with renal cell carcinoma
to present
with distant metastases.
Another carcinoma
that likes to go into,
that likes to spread
hematogenously
is hepatocellular carcinoma.
This likes to invade
the hepatic vein
and then can spread
to distant sites.
A third carcinoma
that likes to spread
hematogenously
is follicular carcinoma
of the thyroid.
And the fourth
is choriocarcinoma.
And choriocarcinoma
is really easy to remember
because what is
choriocarcinoma?
Choriocarcinoma
is a malignancy
of placental tissue.
In particular,
the cells that line
the villi of the placenta.
And those cells
are called trophoblasts.
And so choriocarcinoma
is a malignancy
of trophoblasts.
And guess what trophoblasts
are designed to do
by their nature?
They're designed
to find a blood vessel
and invade into blood vessel.
In fact,
that's the job
of the placenta.
And so choriocarcinoma,
I don't think
it's too hard
to remember
that it's going
to go into the blood
and it's going
to spread hematogenously
because that's sort
of what those cells
are programmed to do
to begin with.
Now a third way
by which cancer
can spread
is by seeding
body cavities.
And that's characteristic
of ovarian carcinoma.
Ovarian carcinoma
has the propensity
to seed body cavities.
It often involves
the omentum
of the abdomen.
And so a classic picture
that can arise
is something like this
where we can clearly see
that we're in the abdomen.
This is a loop of bowel.
And this is cancer
that has completely
replaced the omentum.
Were we to actually
cut through this,
this would be very thick.
And when you cut
through this with a knife,
it sort of has
the consistency of cake.
And so another term
to describe this phenomena
is called omental caking.
And that is an important term
to be familiar with
and I've placed it
in your text as well.
So that concludes
this section
on tumor progression.